Greenland,
the world's largest island,
blanketed by ice 2 mi thick,
and where glaciers and icebergs choke
the fjords.
Today, on the narrow strip between ice
sheet [music] and ocean, 55,000 people
eke out a living.
But amidst their scattered dwellings
lies a mystery from the past.
Now these stones are all that remain of
[music] a lost Viking civilization.
About a thousand years ago, the Vikings,
Norsemen from Scandinavia, established a
colony in Greenland.
For almost five centuries, [music]
they flourished here. Then,
extraordinarily, the settlers
disappeared, leaving behind them a
riddle that scientists, [music]
historians, and archaeologists have
failed to solve until now.
>> The colony in Greenland disappears from
history in about the year 1500. Nobody
knows exactly why or exactly when this
happened. It's one of the great unsolved
mysteries of the Middle Ages.
>> The first settlement to disappear lay on
the west coast [music] of Greenland.
Around 1340, an emissary from the
Vikings home in Norway sailed into this
fjord and what he found amazed and
shocked him.
The emissary's name was Ivar Bardarson.
>> When he arrived there, the place was
empty. There was no one there and he
says in his report,
>> "I saw nobody,
neither Christians nor heathens,
only some wild cattle and sheep, all
running wild."
>> This means that the settlement was
empty. The Norse Greenlanders had left
or died out, probably fairly recently
since the domestic [music] animals were
still there.
>> Bardarson was the first of many who over
the centuries have wondered what could
have happened to make a once prosperous
civilization suddenly disappear.
Today, 650 years later, an international
team of scientists has come to Greenland
hoping to find the answer.
Archaeologists, physicists, chemists,
and botanists are pooling ideas and
resources. Among them, Dr. Bent
Fredskild, a botanist fascinated by the
lost Vikings for more than 40 years.
>> It's a long story.
It started '55
with my first visit and since then I
have spent 29 whole summers in different
places in Greenland.
>> Outside the few small towns, Greenland
has no roads. Like the Vikings, the
scientists must make most journeys by
boat.
>> To help them explain the settlers'
disappearance, the team is excavating a
key Viking site.
In a remote coastal valley, a sheep
farmer has stumbled across the ruins
[music] of a farmstead.
The team of scientists [music]
from Scandinavia, Britain, and the
United States is led by Dr. Jette
[music] Arneborg of the National Museum
of Denmark.
>> The disappearance of the Norse
Greenlanders is a mystery.
Every new generation have new answers,
and I think that's very exciting. And in
a way that reflects that history is very
much alive in our
society today.
>> The team will camp here for a month,
making the most of the few short weeks
of the Arctic summer.
Perhaps this will be the dig that finds
out what really became of the Greenland
Vikings.
>> [music]
>> The investigators know exactly where to
look for clues.
>> [music]
>> Here, they are working through a midden,
or rubbish tip. Every farmstead had one,
and into it generations of Viking
families threw anything from the
leftover bones of yesterday's dinner to
the outgrown treasures of childhood.
>> Can you see? It's a horseman.
We don't know really what those horses
were for, but we
guess that they were toys, children's
toys.
Perhaps they had something
uh
something to do with horses. Yeah, I
don't know.
>> Every object found will eventually be
dated because the archaeologists can
work out when each individual layer of
the midden was laid down.
>> The the very top of the
of the transect is a layer that just
came on on a few years ago. And then
beneath this we have a recent peat
layer.
And then there's the first
Norse layer, one could call it, which
has a lot of charcoal and bone remains
in it.
The the Viking period is actually
documented from all the way from the
bottom until uh
15 cm below the recent surface.
>> The excavations have helped the team
build up a remarkably detailed picture
of life in Greenland at the height of
the Viking civilization.
Judith Jesch of Nottingham University
has gleaned further facts from the few
surviving ancient documents and sagas.
These chronicle how the Norsemen first
came to this unknown land, then on the
outermost edge of the habitable world.
>> The earliest and most reliable source
tells us of a man called Eric [music]
the Red from Norway who had heard of a
country to the west and sailed to find
[music] it and discovered it and called
it Greenland and then went back with 25
ships of settlers.
Eric the Red [music] settled in what's
called the Eastern settlement in
Greenland. And there's also a smaller
settlement in the Western settlement.
Of the 25 ships [music] that went to
Greenland only 14 arrived, but later
colonists kept arriving after that.
>> The archaeologists have established that
the Viking colonists were farmers.
They built houses like this one
reconstructed in Iceland in the style of
their ancestors back in Scandinavia from
turf, stone, and timber.
This is what life was like for the
Greenland Vikings.
>> They lived in small isolated farmhouses,
and you have to remember that it was
dark for most of the year that far
north. So, they would sit indoors and
amuse themselves
by composing poetry, telling stories,
carving toys out of wood and ivory.
Playing chess, perhaps.
>> First and foremost, [music]
the Vikings were farmers.
They built houses, stables, and
cowsheds, usually sheltered in secret
valleys amongst the coastal [music]
hills. They grew fodder and hay for
their animals each summer on the high
pastures.
One task for today's archaeologists
[music]
is to map these settlements.
Here are the remains of a compound one
farmer constructed for the sheep,
cattle, and goats he'd imported from
back home in Scandinavia.
The ruins show that over the years the
population grew.
Before their disappearance, up to 6,000
Vikings occupied Greenland.
In winter, the Vikings lived cheek by
jowl with their animals, sheltering from
the piercing Arctic cold.
Unable to exercise in these cramped
conditions, the animals lost the use of
their legs, and when spring finally
came, they had to be carried out to the
fields to graze.
>> The Vikings lived by subsistence
agriculture in Greenland, and they had
to import a lot of the things that was
necessary to their lifestyle. So, they
had to import timber for their housing,
that to import iron for the the nails to
build their houses with.
Um and in order to get these from
abroad, for instance, from Norway, they
exported Greenland falcons, which were
known as far away as Sicily.
They exported walrus ivory.
And in the early Middle Ages, this was
the only source of ivory. It was
exported throughout Europe.
And carved into beautiful objects found
in churches, crucifixes, caskets,
[music] and the like.
>> For 500 years, the settlers flourished.
With the money from trading, they built
[music] magnificent churches.
This one at Hvalsey is the only one
still partly standing today.
As their prosperity grew, they even sent
a message to the Pope in far-away Rome.
In it, they asked him to send them a
bishop. In exchange, more exotically,
they offered the gift of a polar bear.
But this success did not last.
>> [music]
>> We now know that in the 14th and 15th
centuries, something unexpected made the
Greenland Vikings disappear from their
settlements.
>> The last known communication from
Norse Greenland was in the year 1410
when a party of Icelanders arrived in
Norway having come from Greenland.
While they were there, two of them
[music] uh decided to get married and we
have very detailed records of the
wedding that took place in the church
[music] at Valse on the 16th of
September in 1408. And it said that
there were many people there both
Greenlanders uh of Viking descent and
[music] foreigners.
>> In nomine Patris et Fili et Spiritus
Sancti.
>> It was also done properly. [music] The
bands were read out in church for 3
weeks running before the wedding.
The same Icelanders also witnessed some
dramatic events while they while they
were in Greenland.
Um a man called Kolgrimar uh who had
apparently seduced a married woman using
witchcraft and black arts was sentenced
to death by burning at the stake.
The woman he seduced never really
recovered from this experience and she
died shortly afterwards.
>> After this report, no more was ever
heard from the Greenland Vikings.
But over the next few years, they
vanished apparently into thin air.
>> Okay.
>> Today, the finds from excavations are
all that archaeologists have to go on as
they search for an explanation for the
mysterious disappearance of the
settlers.
>> [snorts]
>> But this hasn't stopped them toying with
some extraordinary theories.
>> One possibility is is the plague [music]
that they died of illness and the colony
was just wiped out.
Another possibility is that they were
kidnapped [music] by pirates.
It's also been suggested that they've um
intermarried with the Inuits, the native
Greenlanders.
>> Other investigators claim the Vikings
perished in a war with the Eskimos,
today's Inuits.
The sagas, the ancient records of Arctic
history, tell of battles lost by the
settlers. In one, 18 Vikings were
slaughtered.
Pioneering excavations [music]
at the beginning of the 20th century
have provided further valuable leads.
From graves in Greenland's Viking
churchyards, archaeologists recovered
human bones and farmhouse middens
yielded thousands of artifacts.
They even found medieval clothing
perfectly preserved in the permafrost
with their colors still fast.
>> [music]
>> Now, eight decades later, the bones are
revealing new clues to the disappearance
of the settlers.
Here at the University of Copenhagen,
where the finds are now kept,
pathologist Dr. Niels Lynnerup has been
studying the skeletons using the latest
forensic techniques.
And he has made a surprising discovery.
During the last years of the
settlements, the Viking's life
expectancy fell. Lynnerup believes this
was caused by a dramatic decline in
people's living conditions and health.
>> We have the remains of about 350 Norse.
The average lifespan was about 30 to 35
years.
But we think maybe there was a decline
throughout the settlement period.
People would be living maybe up to 35
years old and then gradually lifespan
fell by a couple of years throughout the
500 years of settlement.
>> Dr. Lynnerup searched for evidence of
any illness that could have shortened
the Viking's lives. X-rays of the skulls
revealed one telling fact. In the last
years of the colony, many of the Vikings
had suffered from middle ear disease, a
sure sign that their health had
deteriorated.
>> We found that there was a higher
frequency of middle ear disease in the
later settlement period as compared to
the early settlement period.
>> [crying]
[laughter]
>> Again, indicating that living conditions
[music] were getting worse. More and
more people were getting
common diseases as pneumonia. And then
again, that would mean that more were
also dying from that disease.
>> Further analysis of the bones revealed
another [music] telling clue.
>> We also found that there was an
overrepresentation
of young adult female skeletons in the
graveyards.
Which could also indicate [music]
worsened living conditions.
Because we know that young females along
with infants [music] and the very old
are those most susceptible to diseases.
>> Linnærups discoveries point to a crisis.
The people most vital to the future of
the settlements, young women of
childbearing age, were dying off.
And in [music] the silted up ruins of a
farmhouse, the archaeologist found a
chilling pointer to the fate of the
other settlers.
Lying in the [music] kitchen were the
bones of a newborn calf and a Norwegian
Elkhound, a Viking hunting dog.
The bones were covered in knife marks.
Both creatures had been butchered and
eaten.
The investigators knew no Viking would
have slaughtered his hunting dog unless
he faced starvation.
A study of fossilized flies provides
confirmation that a famine raged in
Greenland in the last years of the
Viking colony.
At Sheffield University, Peter Skidmore
has pieced together the story using
flies recovered from rooms at the
farmhouse where the dog bones were
found.
>> Fossilized flies can tell us a very
great deal.
Some of the material from Greenland
that I have examined has been
amazing condition.
I have here a batch of specimens that
Max has extracted from one particular
room in a in a Norse dwelling.
That species, Telomyza flavipes,
only bred in situations that were warm.
It's what they call a thermophilous fly,
and it breeds in decaying animal matter.
The sort of situation that this fly
would require
would be found in a dark, warm room
in those days,
with plenty of droppings, precisely a
description of the Norse living room in
those days.
>> As he'd expected, Skidmore found
warmth-loving flies on the floors of the
bedroom and living room at the
farmhouse. While in the food larder,
another type had flourished. This loved
colder conditions and lived off meat.
But on the top layer of silt formed at
the end of the Viking's occupation, he
found something quite different. The
warmth-loving flies had disappeared and
the cold-loving flesh-eaters had moved
into the bedroom. Skidmore knew what
that meant. They'd gone there to feed on
the dead bodies of the settlers.
>> Purely looking at the flies,
there was a build-up of carrion in the
bedroom.
And it looked all pretty sinister,
really.
That possibly the occupants had died in
the beds.
>> In the hope of discovering the cause
[music] of this tragedy, the scientists
headed towards Greenland's forbidding
interior, to the ice sheet 2 miles deep
and more than a quarter of a million
years old. Here, an extraordinary
scientific feat could provide [music] a
definite solution to the mystery of the
lost Vikings of Greenland.
Greenland is almost entirely covered by
ice. [music]
Scientists speculated that this held
vital clues to the unexplained
disappearance of the Vikings.
The Greenland Ice Sheet Project or GISP
2 involved drilling down through the ice
sheet and extracting a core.
This contains the history of changes in
the Earth's climate over the past
quarter of a million years.
The core [music] is kept in sections in
a giant freezer at the University of New
Hampshire in the United States.
>> Thickness of the ice in the area that we
conducted our study is about 3,000 m. In
fact, it's exactly 3,056.4
m because we drilled right down to the
bedrock.
>> As snow falls on Greenland, it absorbs
chemicals, gases, and dust from the
atmosphere.
Over time, the snow compacts into ice.
Scientists looking at any section of ice
core from the past 250,000 years can
tell precisely what was happening to the
climate at that time.
>> The ice core is a 5.2-in diameter core.
And what's particularly remarkable is
that within any layer, we can recover 50
different measures or descriptions of
what the environment is like. So, here
we have the best-preserved
record of frozen atmosphere for that one
particular year.
>> The ice cores reveal that when the
Vikings [music]
first settled in Greenland around the
year 1000, the climate was exceptionally
fine, but it wasn't to last.
>> There's evidence when the Viking colony
was first established that the weather
was actually rather good. Um there's
even a 13th-century [music] Norwegian
text which says that the weather in
Greenland in the summer at any rate is
nicer than in either Iceland or Norway.
Um but what seems to have happened is
that uh the the weather got gradually
colder. [music]
>> To measure how cold it became, one
scientist analyzed the atoms inside
[music] the ice cores. Dr. Lisa Barlow
of the University of Colorado was
looking for deuterium. Most water
molecules are made out of two hydrogens
and one oxygen atom.
A very small percentage of water
molecules are made out of one hydrogen
and one heavy hydrogen which is called
deuterium and an oxygen molecule. Now
these water molecules with the deuterium
are slightly heavier and so they respond
differently to processes like
evaporation and precipitation.
In warm weather deuterium evaporates
easily into the clouds, but when it's
freezing its heaviness holds it back. As
a result less falls later in the snow.
So as you look through the snow,
if you had a profile from the surface of
the snow and looking down through so
looking down through time, you have this
nice seasonal signal where
in the summer time there's a little bit
more of the deuterium in the winter time
is a little less.
Dr. Barlow found the ice cores from the
end of Viking times contain abnormally
little deuterium. Her conclusion, the
climate grew colder. In fact, Greenland
was hit by a little ice age.
When the Norse traveled to Greenland
during very mild period in Earth's
history, the Medieval Warm Period, the
conditions were relatively mild.
Having lived there for many generations,
they would have been extremely surprised
to suddenly find out in the late 1300s
and early 1400s that things were
changing around them.
But the evidence of the run of cold
summers came only from the ice in the
center [music] of Greenland. To make
sure the climate also changed at the
settlements on the coast, Dr. Henry
Fricke of the University of Michigan
compared the ice core results with data
from the bodies of the Vikings
themselves.
>> He knew that another accurate record of
the weather during their lifetime lay in
their teeth.
>> In my research, I'm taking this one step
further and I'm using the oxygen isotope
ratio of of tooth enamel to act as sort
of
a record or proxy for that of local rain
or snow.
>> [music]
>> And we can do that because
in the case of the Norse, they were
probably getting their drinking water
from
little ponds, streams, meltwater from
snow. So, that water from the surface
gets incorporated into their bodies,
[music] into their blood, and then
eventually into the teeth. So, that the
oxygen isotope ratio of that tooth
enamel can act as a record for what the
temperature was at the time that that
person was living.
>> This tooth comes from a Viking graveyard
in Greenland.
Dr. Fricke only needs a few grains of
its enamel for his tests.
The 650-year-old tooth enamel is mixed
with chemicals and heated to 1400° C.
The resulting gas is then put through a
mass spectrometer.
This measures the oxygen isotope ratio.
Fricke ran a series of tests on teeth
from carbon-dated skeletons of different
ages.
His results confirm a drop in surface
temperature at around the middle of the
14th century.
He noted that this coincided with the
very time the Western settlement was
found to be deserted by the emissary
Ivar Bardarson.
>> This isotopic evidence confirms
the results that the people working on
ice cores are getting. The cooling that
they observe in those ice cores was in
fact lived through by the people right
there on the coast of Greenland.
>> A mini ice age could have delivered the
death blow to the Vikings farming
system.
Lisa Ballo believes it caused their hay
crops to fail, leaving the cattle and
sheep without food for the months ahead.
>> If you have lower summer temperatures,
then that affects the amount of grass
that can be grown. Now, the important
thing about that is not necessarily that
summer, but the fact that these people
are trying to feed their cattle for the
next 9 months of winter on whatever they
can grow in the summer.
>> Proof that the harvest did fail came
once more from Sheffield University and
from an unlikely source.
Fossils of the beetles that lived in the
fields and hay lofts of Viking
Greenland.
When scientists there counted these
fossilized insects, they found that
their numbers had fallen dramatically in
the last years of the settlements. An
irrefutable sign that hay production did
indeed slump to crisis levels.
>> In some of the later samples, there's a
suggestion in changes in the fauna that
the hay field is being denuded.
That either they are so short of hay,
they are over exploiting it, or they're
overgrazing it.
And the reason they're taking too much
hay is that they haven't enough to keep
their animals alive through the winter.
Eventually reach a critical point where
you can't maintain your breeding
population of animals.
And if your stock dies, then you die.
But not everyone blames the
disappearance of the Greenland Vikings
entirely on the mini ice age.
Dr. Bent Fredskild is a Danish botanist.
After working on the mystery for more
than 40 years, he believes that the
Vikings were finding it difficult to
feed their livestock long before
temperatures took their sudden dive in
the 1340s.
On his research trips to Greenland, Dr.
Fredskild took hundreds of mud cores
from lake beds. He found these contained
soil blown off the meadows in Viking
[music] times.
This showed the settlers had overgrazed
the land causing widespread erosion.
>> Yeah, the large
erosion area we are going to
see is just behind this ridge and in
front of the two dark bedrock.
>> In modern times, overgrazing has again
depleted the thin soil and Fredskild
believes the situation was the same in
the Middle Ages.
Then as now, the sheep and cattle ate
away the ground cover once blooming with
plants like the Greenland willow.
>> Here's a large
root of northern willow, the same
species as grown there.
And it has been exposed as a result of
uh severe erosion.
This erosion started because of
uh overgrazing.
The sheep
uh
broke the thin vegetation cover.
>> With the vegetation cover broken, the
harsh wind coming off the inland ice
tears into the soil and blows it away.
Dr. Fredskild believes that by
overgrazing, the Vikings turned [music]
their once fertile pasture into
wasteland.
Frozen,
starving,
with their animals dying around [music]
them, isolated in the northern wastes
behind an ever-growing wall of sea ice,
did the Vikings succumb [music] to a
crisis so insuperable that those who
could not escape simply took to their
beds and [music] waited for the end?
Yet, the people of Greenland's other
civilization, the Thule Inuits, survived
these terrible times.
>> This land is big. It's It's beautiful,
but it's also very harsh.
It's a harsh nature.
So, you have to have some certain skills
to survive, especially in the old days.
The Vikings
didn't really catch the the meaning of
life here.
>> Of the two peoples, the Thule Inuits had
been in Greenland for less time than the
Vikings. Yet, they had all the survival
skills the Vikings lacked.
An extraordinary discovery shows this to
be true.
These mummified bodies of an Inuit
family [music] preserved by the
permafrost date from around the time of
the Vikings' disappearance.
Even in death, their clothing protected
them from the elements.
The discovery of the mummies was soon to
provide a vital clue.
This brings scientists [music] closer to
discovering why, unlike their neighbors,
the Norsemen so tragically failed to
adapt to the new ice age, despite
knowing that it threatened [music] to
destroy them.
>> The onset of a little ice age in the
Middle Ages [music] was a formidable
test to the Viking survival skills, but
they failed to respond to the [music]
challenge. They did too little, too
late.
>> We can see that as as conditions grew
colder in Greenland, the Vikings didn't
actually [music] adapt very well to the
changing conditions. At Herjolfsnes in
in the south of Greenland,
archaeologists have found clothing from
the 15th century.
This is typical [music] woolen clothing
of the latest fashion.
They wore capes, hooded capes with long
tails, which was the height of fashion
at that time.
And that [music] was fine, but it wasn't
warm enough for the conditions that were
prevalent in in that period. [music]
Very near there at the same time,
archaeologists have also found the
mummified bodies of some Inuit people
[music]
who were all dressed appropriately in
furs and hides,
>> [music]
>> and were clearly much better adapted to
survive this mini ice age.
>> It is thought [music] they were on board
an Inuit ship and drowned in some
catastrophic accident at sea.
When their bodies reached shore, they
were mummified by the cold, dry Arctic
winds.
>> [music]
>> Their extraordinary state of
preservation has allowed archaeologists
to study their clothes.
They found them meticulously tailored
from skins, caribou and seals.
Hide thick enough [music] to withstand
the rigors of the harshest climates.
They concluded that as the mini ice age
enveloped them, the Vikings brought
disaster on themselves by failing to
adapt to the lifestyle [music] and ways
of the Inuit.
The Thule Inuits arrived in southern
Greenland from the high Arctic in the
12th and 13th centuries.
They were hunter-gatherers, and today in
the remote areas of Greenland, the men
still live by hunting.
Boys make their first kill before
reaching their teens.
Their quarry can be seal, walrus, polar
bear, or whale.
But these men from the isolated
settlement of Kulusuk are in pursuit of
caribou.
Over the centuries, the diet of the
Inuit has hardly changed. It still
depends on what the hunters bring home.
So, during the mini ice age, the Inuit
didn't go hungry. There was always prey
to be caught.
But the Viking settlers never learned to
hunt and forage for food as successfully
as their Inuit neighbors.
>> The Norse in Greenland certainly
perished in a time of climatic change, a
time where the climate changes were
mostly unfavorable to them. But it's
good to recognize that not everybody in
Greenland perished at the same time. The
Inuit, who by this point were living in
most parts of Greenland, survived quite
nicely as far as we know through the
same period and they were the ancestors
of the modern Greenlandic population
which exists today. So Greenland did not
become uninhabitable for all humans. In
fact, some humans, these hunters, did
fine throughout the same time period.
What it did become though was extremely
hostile to the kind of society the Norse
Greenlanders had constructed, a society
that had all these trappings of medieval
Europe, the society that had its
bishops, its monasteries, its nunneries,
its rich men, its poor men, all the bits
and pieces of medieval Europe which had
come into Greenland at this point were
expensive. They were expensive socially
and they were expensive environmentally
as well.
>> A key question is whether the Vikings
started hunting and fishing as
conditions changed or did they continue
with their old ways, farming cattle and
sheep as they'd always done?
Animal bones from archaeological digs
like this year's from the Eastern
settlement offer some interesting
revelations.
Every fragment discarded while this farm
was occupied was painstakingly gathered
up.
By the time the excavation closed,
50,000 samples were ready to be sent
around the world for analysis and
identification.
Some of the bones have ended up here in
the busy heart of New York at the City
University, joining the collection of
Professor Tom McGovern, the scientist
coordinating the investigation into the
disappearance of the Vikings.
By looking at the bones and the
information about where in the layers
they were found, McGovern can work out
what the people ate and how their diet
changed over time.
>> Got a tray of bones right here where you
can
see some of these animal bones laid out
here. This is a pretty typical set of
remains that you get from an
archaeological excavation.
Some of these things are cattle bones
brought in from Europe. Here's a
little piece of a sheep jaw.
Goats, pigs, dogs, horses. Uh some of
them, however, are animals that are wild
or local. Uh animals like caribou,
animals like seals.
>> But McGovern concludes the Greenland
Vikings only turned to fishing and
hunting when the mini ice age threatened
their food supplies. And even then, they
ate very little food from the sea
compared to their Viking neighbors in
Iceland.
>> In Iceland by late 1200s, early 1300s,
the same period as we're just looking at
this tray here from Greenland. We look
at a tray of a very comparable site from
Iceland, a very small one.
You can see there's again a bunch of
bones here, but they're different.
Fish bones. We have some some birds
present here. We have a little fragments
of whale bones.
But most of this tray is fish, including
one great big ling got in there somehow.
A lot of cod.
>> The presence of a few seal bones suggest
the Vikings did in the end try to adapt
to local conditions and change their
diet. But the archaeological evidence
shows they were still unable to meet all
their needs.
Fossils of blowflies from Viking and
Eskimo middens have convinced
entomologist Peter Skidmore that the
Vikings went hungry while the Inuit had
more food than they could eat.
>> The species that indicate carrion on the
midden are the blowflies.
It appears from the
from the fly remains present that there
was no carrion or even marrow
on the Norse middens.
We know that there was a lot of bone
material.
Um but there was no marrow.
In contrast, the Eskimo middens,
enormous amount of carrion and masses of
marrow.
They had plenty of it.
They were availing themselves of the
seals and the and the fish in the
fjords. The Norse economy seemed to have
been based entirely on the sheep and
cattle.
So, they were there they were taking all
the marrow out of the bones.
And they were scraping clean and
probably boiling all the meat off the
bones as well.
The conclusion that one would be forced
to draw from that would be that the
Eskimos could be perfectly good
with their uh meat products.
>> [music]
>> Now, the scientists were faced with a
further question. Why didn't the Vikings
learn how to hunt from the Inuit?
Tom McGovern
>> [music]
>> blames the church.
>> The church may have played a role in
this strange barrier between these two
cultures.
We might think that the Norse and the
Inuit actually did not coexist in
Greenland at all because there are so
few finds of Inuit objects on Norse
farms.
There are so few examples of Norse
imitation of Inuit adaptation.
Why would a Norse seal hunter not pick
up some of this Inuit technology? And I
think part of the answer is, of course,
if you went and talked to an old
experienced Inuit hunter and persuaded
him to teach you a few secrets, he would
have taught you about how to give water
to the seal when it's brought up from
the ice. He would have taught you about
the proper prayers to say as you're
doing it. Or from the church's
standpoint, what he would have done was
fill your head full of heathen magic.
So, we can easily see scenarios where
the church's interest in in limiting
contact between these two cultures and
regulating it strongly could have had a
really chilling effect in terms of
effective interaction and effective
learning between these these two
different cultures. There certainly was
a barrier maintained between them. It
wasn't accidental. It had to have been
maintained at some considerable trouble
and expense on somebody's part for a
long period.
>> McGovern is convinced [music] that the
church preached that the Inuit should be
avoided because they were not
Christians.
And if the Vikings were forbidden to
speak to their neighbors, they would
never have been able to learn from them
even at a time [music] of crisis.
The number of churches they built in
Greenland is testimony [music] to the
importance that the church played in the
lives of the Viking settlers.
These buildings formed the center not
just of the people's spiritual faith,
>> [music]
>> but also of their society.
It was not for nothing that the
adulterous seducer was [music] burnt to
death in the precincts of the church at
Valse.
And from a grave unearthed in the shadow
of the Viking Cathedral at Gardar in the
Eastern Settlement, comes another
striking indication [music] of the
church's power. It contained the bones
of a bishop. Uniquely, his badges of
office, [music] his holy ring, and his
crosier had been buried in state with
him.
>> There is some evidence that the church
in Greenland held [music] a very firm
grip on the people there
in the 14th century as well as
collecting tides [music] from the farms.
The church also imposed an export tax,
which may have led to deterioration in
income from [music]
trade.
We also hear that many many of the
hunting rights in Greenland belonged to
the church. So, although there was
abundant whale, reindeer, and polar
bears, people could only hunt these
creatures with the permission of the
bishop.
>> At last, from the stones, ice, and
meadows of Greenland, the scientists
have pieced together the tragic story
[music] of the lost Vikings.
The trigger for their downfall was a
sharp change for the worse in the
climate.
The mini [music] ice age that enveloped
them so suddenly caused their crops to
fail and their cattle to starve.
And in the cold, the people's health
began to falter.
Weakened by chest infections and
malnutrition, the young women and
[music] children perished.
In desperation, their elders tried to
adapt to the hunting and fishing
techniques of the Inuit, but through
ignorance or the dictates of an
all-powerful church, they learned too
little, too late.
As famine loomed, they slaughtered their
precious hunting dogs.
>> [music]
>> Thus, the Vikings finally ended all
prospects of surviving [music]
in this unforgiving land.
>> It seems to me very clear that they were
living at the limit of possible
sustained existence.
Had they gone over to
the Inuit lifestyle of
adapting more to their environment, they
probably may have survived. But I think
that they just came to a situation where
it was just not possible to continue
their lifestyle.
>> But there are still some loose ends,
some crucial questions that the
scientists can't fully explain. Although
they found many skeletons [music] in the
graveyards, there were none in the
Viking houses. No one knows why.
>> One thing that's missing from this this
whole grim story of the the end of Norse
Greenland is where is the human bones?
And that's the real question. We have
virtually no human bones from inside
Norse houses that are contemporary with
the end of the settlement. Um
they're just not there.
>> [music]
>> Uh we have plenty of people buried in
the churchyard, but that's the sort of
thing that happens in an orderly fashion
as the society is still functioning.
What happens to last ones?
And the clear answer to this question is
we don't know.
>> Personally, I think [music] the most
likely explanation is that the colony
dwindled until there were very small
numbers and then probably [music]
they sailed away and either never
arrived or went somewhere and we don't
know about where they might have gone.
>> Scientists suspect that in the face of
such adversity,
>> [music]
>> the last of the Viking colonists in
Greenland opted to take refuge on
warmer, more comfortable, friendlier
shores.
They may have tried to return to Norway,
[music]
where their ancestors had come from 500
years before.
They may even have struck out for
America.
But whatever their hoped-for
destination,
they first had treacherous seas to
cross.
>> My own speculation I'll throw into the
pot is that well, if if you were feeling
your in your farm and your whole
settlement was going down, a last resort
might be getting in your boat and try to
to go to the Eastern Settlement, go
somewhere else. And Greenland, as
everyone who's sailed there can attest,
is a dangerous place. And just because
you set out on a journey doesn't mean
you make it. So, one location for the
last of the [music] Norse Greenlanders
may be simply at the bottom of the sea.
>> [music]
[music]